<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <channel>
        <title>Logic Seminar Verona</title>
        <link>https://www.logicverona.it/</link>
        <description><![CDATA[Announcements of talks and workshops]]></description>
        <atom:link href="https://www.logicverona.it//feed.rss" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 15:30:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>Minicourse "Introduction to Type Theory"</title>
    <link>https://www.logicverona.it//2025-10-27.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <h1><a href=/2025-10-27.html>Minicourse "Introduction to Type Theory"</a></h1>
    <section class="header">
        October  8, 2025
    </section>
    <section>
        <p><strong>Introduction to Type Theory</strong><br />
<a href="https://www.nottingham.ac.uk/computerscience/people/thorsten.altenkirch">Thorsten Altenkirch</a> (University of Nottingham)<br />
October 27–31, 2025</p>
<p><em>Abstract</em><br />
Type Theory is at the same time an alternative to set theory as a mathematical foundation and a programming language originally conceived by the Swedish philosopher and mathematician Per Martin-Löf. The course is an introduction to Type Theory which covers the following topics:<br />
</p>
<pre><code>λ-calculus and combinatory logic\
Propositions as types\
Classical vs intuitionistic reasoning\
Dependent types, Π- and Σ-types\
Reasoning in Type Theory, Equality\
Inductive and coinductive types\
Universes and paradoxes\
Homotopy Type Theory\</code></pre>
<p>The Agda system will be used for examples and exercises.</p>
<p><em>Timetable</em><br />
Monday 27th: 16:30-18:30 - Aula G (2 hrs core lectures)<br />
Tuesday 28th: 08:30-10:30 - Aula T.04 (2 hrs core lectures)<br />
Wednesday 29th: 08:30-11:30 - Aula T.04 (2 hrs core lectures + 1 h supplementary lecture)<br />
Friday 31st: 16:30-19:30 - Aula T.04 (3 hrs supplementary lectures)<br />
</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 15:30:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://www.logicverona.it//2025-10-27.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Dipartimento di Informatica</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>CIRM Conference "Synthetic mathematics, logic-affine computation and efficient proof systems"</title>
    <link>https://www.logicverona.it//2025-09-CIRM.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <h1><a href=/2025-09-CIRM.html>CIRM Conference "Synthetic mathematics, logic-affine computation and efficient proof systems"</a></h1>
    <section class="header">
        April 18, 2025
    </section>
    <section>
        <p><strong>Synthetic mathematics, logic-affine computation and efficient proof systems</strong></p>
<p>CIRM - Centre International de Rencontres Mathématiques, Marseille Luminy, France, 8-12 September 2025.</p>
<p>Synthetic frameworks have proved to be pivotal tools at the interface of mathematics and informatics, especially enabling concise formalizations and custom proof systems. Noteworthy achievements include homotopy type theory, synthetic computability theory, and synthetic algebraic geometry. Very similar paradigms characterize the related areas of logic-driven computational algebra and geometry, sheaf models and modern realizability theory, and strong negation for constructive reasoning with negative information. Contrasting yet complementary approaches are about to converge, emphasizing the imperative of unifying theoretical underpinnings with practical implementation. With the proposed seminar we aim to extend and deepen the convergence across disciplinary boundaries by fostering exchange and collaboration among experts and practitioners.</p>
<p>Scientific Committee:<br />
- Andrej Bauer (University of Ljubljana)<br />
- Olivia Caramello (IHES)<br />
- Maria Emilia Maietti (Universita degli Studi di Padova)<br />
- Michael Rathjen (University of Leeds)</p>
<p>Organising Committee:<br />
- Ingo Blechschmidt (University of Augsburg)<br />
- Liron Cohen (Ben-Gurion University of the Negev)<br />
- Thierry Coquand (University of Gothenburg)<br />
- Sara Negri (University of Genoa)<br />
- Peter Schuster (University of Verona)</p>
<p>More details will be available on the <a href="https://conferences.cirm-math.fr/3377.html">conference website</a>.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 12:58:41 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://www.logicverona.it//2025-09-CIRM.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Dipartimento di Informatica</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>SAVE THE DATE! PACM∧N Workshop</title>
    <link>https://www.logicverona.it//2025-05-PACMAN.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <h1><a href=/2025-05-PACMAN.html>SAVE THE DATE! PACM∧N Workshop</a></h1>
    <section class="header">
        April 18, 2025
    </section>
    <section>
        <p><strong>Workshop on Proof, Argumentation, Computation, Modalities And Negation (PACM∧N)</strong></p>
<p>A workshop on Proof, Argumentation, Computation, Modalities And Negation will be held from the 14th to the 16th of May 2025 in Rome, Italy.</p>
<p>Scientific and organizing committee:<br />
- Giulio Fellin (Università di Brescia)<br />
- Roberto Maieli (Università Roma Tre)<br />
- Sara Negri (Università di Genova)<br />
- Peter Schuster (Università di Verona)<br />
- Lorenzo Tortora de Falco (Università Roma Tre)<br />
- Margherita Zorzi (Università di Verona)</p>
<p>This workshop explores the intricate relationship between proof, argumentation, computation, modalities and negation. Participants will investigate sound proof construction, principles of persuasive argumentation, and the role of computation in formalising logical structures. The structured program, comprising expert presentations and interactive discussions, offers a formal venue for participants to advance their understanding of foundational concepts in the interdisciplinary domains of logic, mathematics, computer science, philosophy, and linguistics. We welcome participants to partake in this scholarly exploration, contributing to the collective intellectual progress within these domains.</p>
<p>Location: <a href="https://architettura.uniroma3.it/dipartimento/dove-siamo/">Argiletum (Via della Madonna dei Monti, 40 – 00184 Roma)</a>.</p>
<p>More details will be available on the <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/pacman2025-rome">workshop website</a>.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 12:55:41 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://www.logicverona.it//2025-05-PACMAN.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Dipartimento di Informatica</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Computer Science Seminar</title>
    <link>https://www.logicverona.it//2025-03-26.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <h1><a href=/2025-03-26.html>Computer Science Seminar</a></h1>
    <section class="header">
        March 19, 2025
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>Wednesday, 26 March 2025, <a href="https://www.di.univr.it/?ent=luogo&amp;id=220">Sala Verde</a></p>
<hr />
<p>16:00</p>
<p><a href="https://www.unibo.it/sitoweb/simone.martini/">Simone Martini</a> (Università degli Studi di Bologna)</p>
<p><em>Ascesa e declino del linguaggio totale: PL/I, Ada e i linguaggi estensibili, 1965-1980</em></p>
<p>A cavallo tra gli anni sessanta e settanta ci sono stati tentativi di definire “un” linguaggio di programmazione “totale”, che si sarebbe imposto come unico, rendendo tutti gli altri obsoleti. Esempi di questi tentativi sono PL/I (IBM, 1965), Ada (USA DoD, 1980), ma anche i linguaggi estensibili dei primi anni settanta. Ripercorreremo alcuni momenti di quella vicenda, cercando di comprendere alcuni dei motivi che rendono impraticabile il (mito del) linguaggio totale. Che, anzi, è dannoso. La molteplicità dei linguaggi di programmazione è “il contrario di una maledizione”. È “un dono e una benedizione al di là di ogni immaginazione” (G. Steiner, Errata, 1997).</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 17:55:41 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://www.logicverona.it//2025-03-26.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Dipartimento di Informatica</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Seminar</title>
    <link>https://www.logicverona.it//2025-02-24.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <h1><a href=/2025-02-24.html>Seminar</a></h1>
    <section class="header">
        February 13, 2025
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>Monday, 24 February 2025, <a href="https://www.di.univr.it/?ent=luogo&amp;id=33">Aula L</a></p>
<hr />
<p>16:30</p>
<p><a href="https://jlwrigley.github.io/">Joshua L. Wrigley</a> (Université Paris Cité)</p>
<p><em>A topos-theoretic perspective on completions of doctrines</em></p>
<p>Lawvere doctrines are an intuitive extension of Lindenbaum-Tarski algebras from propositional logic to predicate logic, where the role of logical quantifiers is captured by a pair of adjoint functions.</p>
<p>In recent years, there has been increasing interest in the field of ‘completing’ doctrines to richer syntax, e.g. Trotta’s existential completion. We will describe a topos-theoretic framework for completing doctrines to subfragments of geometric logic.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2025 17:55:41 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://www.logicverona.it//2025-02-24.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Dipartimento di Informatica</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Seminar</title>
    <link>https://www.logicverona.it//2025-01-29.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <h1><a href=/2025-01-29.html>Seminar</a></h1>
    <section class="header">
        January 18, 2025
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>Wednesday, 29 January 2025, <a href="https://www.di.univr.it/?ent=luogo&amp;id=28&amp;lang=en">Aula C</a></p>
<hr />
<p>11:00</p>
<p><a href="https://profs.scienze.univr.it/~sala/">Pietro Sala</a> (Università di Verona)</p>
<p><em>Concatenation is All You Need (to avoid!)</em></p>
<p>The emptiness problem for generalized regular expressions has been extensively studied, with the seminal work of Stockmeyer establishing non-elementary lower bounds for the case of expressions without the Kleene star operator [1]. This complexity result has profound connections to temporal logic, specifically through the relationship between language concatenation and the chop modality in interval temporal logic under homogeneity assumptions [2]. In this talk, we investigate an alternative formulation where we replace the binary concatenation operator with two unary operators: prefix (begins) and suffix (ends) [3]. We examine how this modification affects the computational complexity of the emptiness problem, providing insights into the structural properties that contribute to the complexity of the problem. Our analysis sheds new light on how various combinations of operators affect the computational complexity of decision problems for regular languages.</p>
<p>[1] Larry Joseph Stockmeyer. The complexity of decision problems in automata theory and logic.
PhD thesis, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 1974. URL: http://hdl.handle.net/1721.
1/15540.</p>
<p>[2] Joseph Halpern, Zohar Manna, and Ben Moszkowski. A hardware semantics based on temporal
intervals. In Josep Diaz, editor, Automata, Languages and Programming, pages 278-291, Berlin,
Heidelberg, 1983. Springer Berlin Heidelberg. doi: 10.1007/BFB0036915.</p>
<p>[3] Dario Della Monica, Angelo Montanari, Gabriele Puppis, and Pietro Sala.
The Logic of Prefixes and Suffixes is Elementary under Homogeneity. LICS 2023: 1-12</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2025 10:55:41 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://www.logicverona.it//2025-01-29.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Dipartimento di Informatica</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Department Seminar</title>
    <link>https://www.logicverona.it//2025-01-28.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <h1><a href=/2025-01-28.html>Department Seminar</a></h1>
    <section class="header">
        January 11, 2025
    </section>
    <section>
        <p><a href="https://www.di.univr.it/?ent=seminario&amp;id=6488&amp;lang=en">Seminario del Dipartimento di Informatica, Università di Verona</a></p>
<p>Tuesday, 28 January 2025, <a href="https://www.di.univr.it/?ent=luogo&amp;id=24&amp;lang=en">Aula F</a></p>
<hr />
<p>16:30</p>
<p><a href="https://www.math.unibe.ch/ueber_uns/personen/prof_dr_metcalfe_george/index_ger.html">George Metcalfe</a> (University of Bern)</p>
<p><em>Equational Theories of Idempotent Semifields</em></p>
<p>(Joint work with Simon Santschi)</p>
<p>This talk will be about idempotent semifields, which, from a purely algebraic perspective are just lattice-ordered groups formulated in a restricted language with the group multiplication, neutral element, and lattice-join operation. We will see that although countably infinitely many equational theories of lattice-ordered groups have a finite equational basis, no non-trivial equational theory of idempotent semifields has this property. On the other hand, as in the case of lattice-ordered groups, there are continuum-many equational theories of classes of idempotent semifields. Finally, we will relate the problem of deciding equations in the class of idempotent semifields to the problem of deciding if there exists a right order on a free group satisfying a given finite set of inequalities, and show that these problems are, respectively, co-NP-complete and NP-complete.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2025 10:55:41 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://www.logicverona.it//2025-01-28.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Dipartimento di Informatica</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Seminar</title>
    <link>https://www.logicverona.it//2024-11-27.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <h1><a href=/2024-11-27.html>Seminar</a></h1>
    <section class="header">
        November 13, 2024
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>Wednesday, 27 November 2024, <a href="https://www.di.univr.it/?ent=luogo&amp;id=32&amp;lang=en">Aula Gino Tessari</a></p>
<hr />
<p>17:00</p>
<p><a href="https://www.math.is.tohoku.ac.jp/~nemototakako/">Takako Nemoto</a> (Tohoku University)</p>
<p><em>Priority method over intuitionistic logic</em></p>
<p>In this talk, we consider how much non-constructive principles are sufficient for Friedberg-Muchinik construction of degree d such that 0&lt;d&lt;0’.
We will see that the only point we need a non-constructive principle is to show
“if a recursive set S of natural number has finite cardinality, then S has an upper bound”,
which requires ^0_1 law of excluded middle.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 10:55:41 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://www.logicverona.it//2024-11-27.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Dipartimento di Informatica</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Categorical Logic and Constructive Mathematics</title>
    <link>https://www.logicverona.it//2024-10-23-workshop.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <h1><a href=/2024-10-23-workshop.html>Categorical Logic and Constructive Mathematics</a></h1>
    <section class="header">
        October  2, 2024
    </section>
    <section>
        <p><strong>Categorical Logic and Constructive Mathematics</strong></p>
<p>We are excited to announce a Day of Logic at the Department of Computer Science, University of Verona (Strada le Grazie 15 - 37134 Verona) on Wednesday, October 23, 2024.
The event, titled “Categorical Logic and Constructive Mathematics,” is scheduled to start at 9:15 AM in Aula M and to continue until the late afternoon.</p>
<p>Speakers:<br />
- Iosif Petrakis (University of Verona)<br />
- Giulio Fellin (University of Brescia)<br />
- Francesco Ciraulo (University of Padua)<br />
- Marco Benini (University of Insubria)<br />
- <em>Logic seminar:</em> Hajime Ishihara (Toho University)<br />
- <em>Department seminar:</em> Tarmo Uustalu (Reykjavik University &amp; Tallinn University of Technology)</p>
<p><a href="https://univr-my.sharepoint.com/:b:/g/personal/giulio_fellin_univr_it/EUEAHTEqrWNGn1-i6RvntTABhgl_xqVgPMV4wVORrdTEew?e=p1VDw9">Click here to download the full schedule and abstracts.</a></p>
<p><a href="https://mega.nz/folder/ssoTQIJI#qbB1CZdIWSBSamUsX6oRXA">Click here to download the slides.</a></p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 18:55:41 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://www.logicverona.it//2024-10-23-workshop.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Dipartimento di Informatica</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Minicourse "Substructural Logics à la Lambek – Proof Theory and Categorical Semantics"</title>
    <link>https://www.logicverona.it//2024-10-21-minicourse.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <h1><a href=/2024-10-21-minicourse.html>Minicourse "Substructural Logics à la Lambek – Proof Theory and Categorical Semantics"</a></h1>
    <section class="header">
        October  2, 2024
    </section>
    <section>
        <p><strong>Substructural Logics à la Lambek: Proof Theory and Categorical Semantics</strong><br />
<a href="https://cs.ioc.ee/~tarmo/">Tarmo Uustalu</a> (Reykjavik University &amp; Tallinn University of Technology)<br />
October 21–30, 2024</p>
<p><em>Abstract</em><br />
In the 1960s, Joachim Lambek pioneered an approach to substructural logics that unifies proof theory and category theory, motivated by linguistics. ‘Substructural’ means here that some basic principles like “A implies true,” “A implies A and A,” and “A and B imply B and A” do not hold. In sequent calculus terms, this corresponds to the absence of the structural rules of left weakening, contraction, and exchange, indicating that logic is more about resources than truth. What is now known as Lambek calculus is a noncommutative intuitionistic linear logic with a (multiplicative) conjunction and two implications, left and right.<br />
In this minicourse, I will review this approach first on Lambek calculus and a number of variations of it. Then I will focus on skew logics—logics that are even weaker than substructural in that the conjunction connective is only semiunital and semiassociative.<br />
The course will be self-contained. Basic knowledge of classical and intuitionistic logic (Hilbert-style systems and sequent calculi) is desirable for good intuitions. I will introduce the necessary ingredients of proof theory and category theory.</p>
<p><em>Timetable</em><br />
Monday, 21: 11:30–13:30 in Aula D<br />
Tuesday, 22: 8:30–10:30 in Aula C<br />
Friday, 25: 15:30–18:30 in Aula B<br />
Monday, 28: 11:30–13:30 in Aula D<br />
Tuesday, 29: 8:30–10:30 in Aula C<br />
Wednesday, 30: 10:30–11:30 in Aula M</p>
<p><em>Material</em><br />
You can access the material <a href="https://cs.ioc.ee/~tarmo/verona24/">here</a>.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 15:30:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://www.logicverona.it//2024-10-21-minicourse.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Dipartimento di Informatica</dc:creator>
</item>

    </channel>
</rss>
