<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <channel>
        <title>Logic Seminar Verona</title>
        <link>https://www.logicverona.it/</link>
        <description><![CDATA[Announcements of talks and workshops]]></description>
        <atom:link href="https://www.logicverona.it//feed.rss" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 May 2020 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>Seminar</title>
    <link>https://www.logicverona.it//2020-05-14-seminar.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <h1><a href=/2020-05-14-seminar.html>Seminar</a></h1>
    <section class="header">
        May 13, 2020
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>Thursday, May 14th, 2020, 11:00, on Zoom.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.di.univr.it/?ent=persona&amp;id=40478&amp;lang=en&amp;action=edit">Giulio Fellin</a> (Universities of Verona, Trento and Helsinki)<br />
<em>Modal Logic for Induction</em> (j.w.w. Sara Negri and Peter Schuster)</p>
<p><em>Abstract:</em> We use modal logic to obtain syntactical, proof-theoretic versions of transfinite induction as axioms or rules within an appropriate labelled sequent calculus. While transfinite induction proper, also known as Noetherian induction, can be represented by a rule, the variant in which induction is done up to an arbitrary but fixed level happens to correspond to the Gödel–Löb axiom of provability logic. To verify the practicability of our approach in actual practice, we give a fairly universal pattern for proof transformation and test its use in several cases. Among other things, we give a direct and elementary syntactical proof of the theorem that the Gödel–Löb axiom characterises precisely the well-founded and transitive Kripke frames.</p>
<p>The seminar will be held on Zoom. In order to get access to the Zoom meeting, please contact <a href="http://www.di.univr.it/?ent=persona&amp;id=21404&amp;lang=en">Peter Schuster</a>.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2020 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://www.logicverona.it//2020-05-14-seminar.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Dipartimento di Informatica</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Compact Course "Program Extraction"</title>
    <link>https://www.logicverona.it//2020-05-25-short-course.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <h1><a href=/2020-05-25-short-course.html>Compact Course "Program Extraction"</a></h1>
    <section class="header">
        January 30, 2020
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>The minicourse “Program Extraction” by Monika Seisenberger will be held on-line from 25th to 29th May 2020.</p>
<p>Registration will be required by 22nd May. To register please send an email to Franziskus Wiesnet: franziskus.wiesnet(at)unitn.it</p>
<p><strong>Program Extraction</strong><br />
<a href="https://www.swansea.ac.uk/staff/science/computer-science/m.seisenberger/">Monika Seisenberger</a> (Swansea University)</p>
<p><em>Part 1. Extraction of Programs from Constructive Proofs</em><br />
1.1 Introduction, Curry Howard-Correspondence, Realizability Interpretation<br />
1.2 Tool Support, Examples, Extension to Inductive Definitions</p>
<p><em>Part 2. Extraction of Programs from Classical Proofs</em><br />
2.1 A-Translation, Choice principles<br />
2.2 Applications for Both Parts</p>
<p><strong>Timetable</strong><br />
Tuesday, May 26: 8:40-10:20<br />
Wednesday, May 27: 8:40-10:20<br />
Thursday, May 28: 8:40-10:20<br />
Friday, May 29: 15:00-16:00</p>
<p>The course will be completed by a seminar talk on Friday, May 29 at 16:00-17:00.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2020 15:30:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://www.logicverona.it//2020-05-25-short-course.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Dipartimento di Informatica</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>CANCELED COMPACT COURSE</title>
    <link>https://www.logicverona.it//2020-03-09-short-course.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <h1><a href=/2020-03-09-short-course.html>CANCELED COMPACT COURSE</a></h1>
    <section class="header">
        January 30, 2020
    </section>
    <section>
        <p><strong>ATTENTION! The compact course below was canceled</strong></p>
<p>The course will take place on March 9-27, 2020. Timetable below.</p>
<p><strong>Category theory and point-free topology</strong></p>
<p>The Compact Course “Category Theory and Point-Free Topology” is primarily aimed at both undergraduate, graduate and postgraduate students in mathematics with an interest in the intersection between logic, algebra and topology. The event will take place at the Department of Computer Science of the University of Verona, located in Strada le Grazie 15, Verona (Italy).</p>
<p><strong>Lecturer</strong><br />
<a href="http://www.normalesup.org/~henry/">Simon Henry</a> (University of Ottawa)</p>
<p><strong>Summary</strong><br />
“Point-free topology” is the theory of “locales”. They are a type of spaces, very similar to topological spaces, except that they might not have an underlying set of points. Locales that have enough points are the same as topological spaces, but some locales have no points and are completely new objects. We will see how many notions and constructions of ordinary topology carry over to locales. Later in the course I will talk about the internal logic of categories of sheaves, which provide an extremely powerful tool to work with locales. I will explain how these mysterious “spaces without points” are closely connected to ‘forcing’ in set theory, as well as the strong connection between the the theory of locales and intuitionistic mathematics. The course will start with a basic introduction to category theory, including limits and co-limits, epi and monomorphisms, adjoint functors and adjoint functor theorem, etc. The theory of locales will give many illustrations and interesting example of these concepts.</p>
<p><strong>Timetable</strong><br />
Monday, March 9, 13:40-16:10, Aula M.<br />
Wednesday, March 11, 13:40-15:20, Aula G.<br />
Friday, March 13, 13:40-16:10, Sala Riunioni Secondo Piano.<br />
Monday, March 16, 13:40-16:10, Aula M.<br />
Wednesday, March 18, 13:40-15:20, Aula G.<br />
Friday, March 20, 13:40-16:10, Sala Riunioni Secondo Piano.<br />
Monday, March 23, 13:40-16:10, Aula M.<br />
Wednesday, March 25, 13:40-15:20, Aula G.<br />
Friday, March 27, 13:40-16:10, Sala Riunioni Secondo Piano.</p>
<p><strong>Registration</strong><br />
Participation is free. Participants not affiliated at the University of Verona are kindly asked to register by sending an e-mail to <a href="giulio.fellin@univr.it">Giulio Fellin</a> no later than 27 February 2020.</p>
<p><strong>Acknowledgements</strong><br />
This compact course is run as part of the “<a href="http://www.di.univr.it/?ent=ciclosem&amp;idC=147">Mathematics Mini-Courses</a>” of the University of Verona, and within the projects “<a href="https://www.templeton.org/grant/a-new-dawn-of-intuitionism-mathematical-and-philosophical-advances">A New Dawn of Intuitionism: Mathematical and Philosophical Advances</a>” (ID 60842) of the John Templeton Foundation, and “Reducing complexity in algebra, logic, combinatorics - REDCOM” belonging to the programme “Ricerca Scientifica di Eccellenza 2018” of the Fondazione Cariverona.</p>
<p><strong>Contact</strong><br />
<a href="peter.schuster@univr.it">peter.schuster@univr.it</a><br />
<a href="giulio.fellin@univr.it">giulio.fellin@univr.it</a><br />
<a href="http://www.di.univr.it/?ent=seminario&amp;id=5076&amp;idC=70">Course page on univr.it</a></p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2020 14:30:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://www.logicverona.it//2020-03-09-short-course.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Dipartimento di Informatica</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Departmental Seminar</title>
    <link>https://www.logicverona.it//2020-02-12-departmental-seminar.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <h1><a href=/2020-02-12-departmental-seminar.html>Departmental Seminar</a></h1>
    <section class="header">
        January 23, 2020
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>Wednesday, 12. February 2020, 16:30, Aula I.</p>
<p><a href="https://unimap.unipi.it/cercapersone/dettaglio.php?ri=4393">Enrico Moriconi</a> (Università degli Studi di Pisa)<br />
<em>Remarks on Sequent Calculus</em></p>
<p><a href="https://www.logicverona.it/files/documenti932216.pdf">Abstract</a></p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2020 22:45:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://www.logicverona.it//2020-02-12-departmental-seminar.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Dipartimento di Informatica</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Seminar</title>
    <link>https://www.logicverona.it//2019-11-27-seminar.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <h1><a href=/2019-11-27-seminar.html>Seminar</a></h1>
    <section class="header">
        November 27, 2019
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>Wednesday, November 27th, 2019, 15:30, Sala riunioni secondo piano.</p>
<p><a href="https://webapps.unitn.it/du/en/Persona/PER0179811">Davide Trotta</a> (Università degli Studi di Trento)<br />
<em>Doctrines in categorical logic and the existential completion</em></p>
<p><em>Abstract:</em> The notion of hyperdoctrine was introduced by F.W. Lawvere in a series of seminal papers to synthesize the structural properties of logical systems. His crucial intuition was to consider logical languages and theories as indexed categories and to study their 2-categorical properties. For instance, connectives and quantifiers are determined by adjunctions. In this seminar we introduce the notions of primary and existential doctrine, which generalize that of hyperdoctrine, and we present the existential completion. In particular we show how we can add left adjoints along certain functors to a primary doctrine obtaining an existential doctrine. Moreover we show that the 2-monad obtained from this free construction is lax-idempotent, and that the 2-category of existential doctrines is isomorphic to the 2-category of algebras for this 2-monad. Finally we extend the notion of exact completion of an elementary existential doctrine to an arbitrary elementary doctrine.</p>
<hr />
<p>Wednesday, November 27th, 2019, 16:45, Sala riunioni secondo piano.</p>
<p>Branko Nikolić (Macquarie University, Sydney, Australia)<br />
<em>On Directed Colimits of Hilbert Spaces</em></p>
<p><em>Abstract:</em> We will show that the category of Hilbert spaces and contractions has directed colimits, and that tensoring preserves them. We will also discuss (problems with) the generalization to bounded maps.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2019 13:07:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://www.logicverona.it//2019-11-27-seminar.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Dipartimento di Informatica</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Seminar</title>
    <link>https://www.logicverona.it//2019-10-24-seminar.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <h1><a href=/2019-10-24-seminar.html>Seminar</a></h1>
    <section class="header">
        October 24, 2019
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>Tuesday, October 29th, 2019, 16:10, Aula C.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.uninsubria.it/hpp/roberta.bonacina">Roberta Bonacina</a> (Università degli Studi dell’Insubria)<br />
<em>A simpler semantics for a large fragment of Homotopy Type Theory</em></p>
<p><em>Abstract:</em> The standard homotopical interpretation for homotopy type theory is deep and useful, but it sounds odd that the full power of higher-order category theory is needed to describe what is a piece "computable’’ mathematics. We show that those complex categorical tools are not necessary, by proposing a novel semantics, based on 1-category theory, for a big fragment of homotopy type theory which contains the whole Martin-Löf type theory and some higher inductive types. We also describe some proof theoretic results for this system; in particular, we prove a normalisation theorem, extending Girard’s reducibility candidates technique.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2019 13:07:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://www.logicverona.it//2019-10-24-seminar.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Dipartimento di Informatica</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Departmental Seminar</title>
    <link>https://www.logicverona.it//2019-09-30-departmental-seminar.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <h1><a href=/2019-09-30-departmental-seminar.html>Departmental Seminar</a></h1>
    <section class="header">
        September 30, 2019
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>Thursday, September 10th, 2019, 16:30, Sala Verde.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.fmi.uni-jena.de/Beyersdorff.html">Olaf Beyersdorff</a> (Friedrich Schiller University, Jena)<br />
<em>Solving and Proof Complexity for SAT and QBF</em></p>
<p><em>Abstract:</em> SAT and QBF solvers have become ubiquitous tools for the solution of hard computational problems from almost all application domains. In this talk we explain the underlying algorithmic principles of solving, both for propositional satisfiability (SAT) and for the more complex case of quantified Boolean formulas (QBF). Particular emphasis will be placed on how these solving approaches can be modelled proof theoretically and which techniques are available to evaluate their proof complexity.</p>
<p><em>Bio:</em> Since 2018 Olaf Beyersdorff is Professor of Theoretical Computer Science at the Friedrich Schiller University Jena. His research interests are in algorithms, complexity, computational logic, and in particular proof complexity. Before coming to Jena he spent six years at the University of Leeds, as Professor of Computational Logic (2017–18), Associate Professor (2015–17), and Lecturer (2012–15). Since 2018 he is a visiting professor at the University of Leeds. Before that he was a visiting professor (2011/12) and visiting researcher (2009/10) at Sapienza University Rome, Lecturer at Leibniz University Hanover (2007–12) and postdoc at Humboldt University Berlin (2006/07). Beyersdorff obtained a PhD from Humboldt University Berlin in 2006 and completed the habilitation at Leibniz University Hanover in 2011.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 13:07:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://www.logicverona.it//2019-09-30-departmental-seminar.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Dipartimento di Informatica</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Seminar talks</title>
    <link>https://www.logicverona.it//2019-05-30-seminar-talks.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <h1><a href=/2019-05-30-seminar-talks.html>Seminar talks</a></h1>
    <section class="header">
        May 30, 2019
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>Friday, 31 May 2019, 10:30.</p>
<p>Four seminar talks will be given as part of the lecture course <a href="https://www.unitn.it/drmath/46/courses">Proofs and Computations</a>:</p>
<p>Giulio Fellin (University of Verona)<br />
<em>NID and Fullness</em></p>
<p>Marco Girardi (University of Trento)<br />
<em>Diagonal Arguments in Cartesian Closed Categories</em></p>
<p>Luca Pasetto (University of Verona)<br />
<em>Incompleteness via the Halting Problem</em></p>
<p>Francesco Sentieri (University of Verona)<br />
<em>Grothendieck Universes and Strongly Inaccessible Cardinals</em></p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2019 20:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://www.logicverona.it//2019-05-30-seminar-talks.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Dipartimento di Informatica</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Departmental Seminar</title>
    <link>https://www.logicverona.it//2019-03-27-departmental-seminar.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <h1><a href=/2019-03-27-departmental-seminar.html>Departmental Seminar</a></h1>
    <section class="header">
        March 27, 2019
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>Wednesday, 10. April 2019, 15:00, Aula M.</p>
<p><a href="https://www1.maths.leeds.ac.uk/~rathjen/">Michael Rathjen</a> (University of Leeds)<br />
<em>Graph Theory and the Transfinite</em></p>
<p>A bit more than a 100 years ago, as a response to the foundational crisis in mathematics, Hermann Weyl published his “Das Kontinuum” in which he tried to rebuild mathematics from a stance that assumes the existence of the set of natural numbers as an actual completed infinity but no higher infinities. Much later in the 1970s, logicians began to systematically scour various chunks of ordinary mathematics to determine the existential commitments to the infinite that they required. This is known as “Reverse Mathematics”. To put it roughly, it turned out that most of “ordinary” mathematics didn’t need more than what Weyl had assumed. However, there are some notable exceptions. In particular graph theory sports some very nice theorems that require more of the transfinite. The talk will discuss some famous theorems and their relationships with the infinite world.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 27 Mar 2019 13:07:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://www.logicverona.it//2019-03-27-departmental-seminar.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Dipartimento di Informatica</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Seminar</title>
    <link>https://www.logicverona.it//2019-03-27-seminar-4.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <h1><a href=/2019-03-27-seminar-4.html>Seminar</a></h1>
    <section class="header">
        March 27, 2019
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>Wednesday, 3. April 2019, 10:30, Sala Riunioni (2nd floor).</p>
<p>Satoru Niki (Japan Advanced Institute of Science and Technology)<br />
<em>Empirical Negation and Beth Semantics</em></p>
<p>The negation in intuitionistic logic has a ‘future-oriented’ character, as elucidated by the valuation in Kripke models. Its application in mathematical contexts has been validated by the success of constructive mathematics. Its applicability in non-mathematical contexts, in contrast, is argued to have some problems. The existence of a different, ‘empirical’ notion of negation within the framework of intuitionistic logic has been discussed by Heyting, Dummett and others. De (2013) proposed empirical negation as falsity at the bottom root of a Kripke model, and De and Omori (2014) gave the axiomatisation of this logic.</p>
<p>In this talk, I will discuss how the choice of semantics in formulating empirical negation affects the logic one obtains, with Beth semantics as a particular example. This is followed by an examination of arithmetic with empirical negation.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 27 Mar 2019 12:14:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://www.logicverona.it//2019-03-27-seminar-4.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Dipartimento di Informatica</dc:creator>
</item>

    </channel>
</rss>
