<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <channel>
        <title>Logic Seminar Verona</title>
        <link>https://www.logicverona.it/</link>
        <description><![CDATA[Announcements of talks and workshops]]></description>
        <atom:link href="https://www.logicverona.it//feed.rss" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 May 2023 12:55:41 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>Seminars</title>
    <link>https://www.logicverona.it//2023-05.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <h1><a href=/2023-05.html>Seminars</a></h1>
    <section class="header">
        May  3, 2023
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>Tuesday, 9 May 2023</p>
<hr />
<p>14:30, <a href="https://www.dbt.univr.it/?ent=luogo&amp;id=4">Aula E (Ca’ Vignal 1)</a>.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ingo-blechschmidt.eu/">Ingo Blechschmidt</a> (Universität Augsburg)</p>
<p><em>Synthetic scheme theory: a simpler framework for algebraic geometry</em></p>
<p><strong>Abstract:</strong> TBA</p>
<hr />
<p>16:30, <a href="https://www.di.univr.it/?ent=luogo&amp;id=32">Aula Gino Tessari (Ca’ Vignal 2)</a>.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.cis.uni-muenchen.de/~leiss/">Hans Leiß</a> (Universität München)</p>
<p>_Algebraic Representation of the Fixed-Point Closure of *-continuous Kleene Algebras_</p>
<p><strong>Abstract:</strong> The theorem of Chomsky and Schützenberger says that each context-free language L over a finite alphabet X is the image of the intersection of a regular language R over X+Y and the context-free Dyck-language D over X+Y of strings with balanced brackets from Y under the bracket-erasing homomorphism from the monoid of strings over X+Y to that of strings over X.</p>
<p>Within Hopkins’ algebraization of formal language theory we show that the algebra C(X) of context-free languages over X has an isomorphic copy in a suitable tensor product of the algebra R(X) of regular languages over X with a quotient of R(Y) by a congruence describing bracket matches and mismatches. It follows that all context-free languages over X can be defined by regular(!) expressions over X+Y where the letters of X commute with the brackets of Y, thereby providing a substitute for a fixed-point-operator.</p>
<p>This generalizes the theorem of Chomsky and Schützenberger and leads to an algebraic representation of the fixed-point closure of *-continuous Kleene algebras.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 03 May 2023 12:55:41 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://www.logicverona.it//2023-05.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Dipartimento di Informatica</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Seminar</title>
    <link>https://www.logicverona.it//2023-03-21.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <h1><a href=/2023-03-21.html>Seminar</a></h1>
    <section class="header">
        March  7, 2023
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>Tuesday, 21 March 2023, <a href="https://www.di.univr.it/?ent=luogo&amp;id=31">Aula I (Ca’ Vignal 2)</a>.</p>
<p>15:00</p>
<p><a href="https://www.sns.it/it/persona/matteo-tesi">Matteo Tesi</a> (Scuola Normale Superiore, Pisa)</p>
<p><em>Quantificatori moltiplicativi, esponenziali e cut-elimination</em> (j.w.w. Carlo Nicolai e Mario Piazza)</p>
<p><strong>Abstract:</strong> L’aggiunta di un predicato di verità governato da regole ingenue conduce spesso a sistemi contraddittori. Un metodo per recuperare la consistenza consiste nell’adottare una logica priva di contrazione: questa strada è stata seguita - tra gli altri - da Grishin e Cantini. Successivamente un ulteriore approccio basato su quantificatori moltiplicativi è stato proposto da Zardini, ma il sistema si è rivelato inconsistente. Nel presente talk proponiamo un’analisi della logica dei quantificatori moltiplicativi. In primo luogo offriamo una presentazione consistente di un sistema con predicato di verità decitazionale con quantificatori additivi. In seguito mostriamo come gli esponenziali (! e ?) possano essere interpretati in modo corretto e fedele mediante l’uso dei quantificatori moltiplicativi. Infine proponiamo una dimostrazione sintattica di eliminazione del taglio per un calcolo con quantificatori moltiplicativi. L’analisi della strategia porterà alla luce la presenza di contrazione implicita nelle regole dei quantificatori.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 07 Mar 2023 12:55:41 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://www.logicverona.it//2023-03-21.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Dipartimento di Informatica</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Seminar</title>
    <link>https://www.logicverona.it//2023-01-23.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <h1><a href=/2023-01-23.html>Seminar</a></h1>
    <section class="header">
        January 17, 2023
    </section>
    <section>
        <p>Monday, 23 January 2023, <a href="https://www.dbt.univr.it/?ent=luogo&amp;id=24">Aula F (Ca’ Vignal 1)</a>.</p>
<hr />
<p>15:00</p>
<p><a href="https://fp.jaist.ac.jp/public/Default2.aspx?id=688&amp;l=1">Tatsuji Kawai</a> (Japan Advanced Institute of Science and Technology)</p>
<p><em>Predicative theory of stably locally compact locales</em></p>
<p>We give a predicative presentation of stably locally compact locales, the class of locales which includes locally compact regular locales (e.g., localic reals) as its subclass. In our setting, a stably locally compact locale is presented as a quasi-proximity lattice, a quasi-bounded distributive lattice (distributive lattice without top) together with a certain idempotent relation on it. Using this structure, we construct a coreflection from the category of locally compact regular locales and cobounded maps to that of stably locally compact locales and perfect maps. The construction of this coreflection generalizes Dedekind’s construction of real numbers as pairs of a lower and an upper cut.</p>
<hr />
<p>16:30</p>
<p><a href="https://fp.jaist.ac.jp/public/Default2.aspx?id=48&amp;l=1">Hajime Ishihara</a> (Japan Advanced Institute of Science and Technology)</p>
<p><em>Reflexive combinatory algebras</em></p>
<p>We introduce the notion of reflexivity for combinatory algebras. Reflexivity can be thought of as an equational counterpart of the Meyer-Scott axiom of combinatory models, which indeed allows us to characterise an equationally definable counterpart of combinatory models. This new structure, called strongly reflexive combinatory algebra, admits a finite axiomatisation with seven closed equations, and the structure is shown to be exactly the retract of combinatory models. Lambda algebras can be characterised as strongly reflexive combinatory algebras which are stable.</p>
<p>This is a joint work with Marlou M. Gijzen and Tatsuji Kawai.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2023 12:55:41 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://www.logicverona.it//2023-01-23.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Dipartimento di Informatica</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Compact Course</title>
    <link>https://www.logicverona.it//2021-06-compact-course.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <h1><a href=/2021-06-compact-course.html>Compact Course</a></h1>
    <section class="header">
        June  1, 2021
    </section>
    <section>
        <p><strong>On the Algebra of Logic</strong><br />
<a href="https://moraschini.github.io/index.html">Tommaso Moraschini</a> (University of Barcelona)</p>
<p>The minicourse <a href="https://www.di.univr.it/?ent=seminario&amp;id=5406&amp;idC=163">On the Algebra of Logic</a> [2 ETCS Mat/01] by Tommaso Moraschini, University of Barcelona, is being videoregistered from now on.</p>
<p>Attendees are expected to have verified, refreshed or acquired adequate basic knowledge of universal algebra before following the <a href="https://moraschini.github.io/teaching.html">videolectures</a> by working through chapters 1 and 2 of the <a href="https://moraschini.github.io/teaching.html">course notes</a>.</p>
<p>Members of the University of Verona are kindly asked to register for the course mailing list by writing to <a href="https://www.di.univr.it/?ent=persona&amp;id=40478&amp;lang=it">Giulio Fellin</a>. Students of the University of Verona who want to obtain credits for this course also in the future should contact prof. <a href="https://www.di.univr.it/?ent=persona&amp;id=21404">Peter Schuster</a>.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://www.logicverona.it//2021-06-compact-course.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Dipartimento di Informatica</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Seminar</title>
    <link>https://www.logicverona.it//2021-06-04.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <h1><a href=/2021-06-04.html>Seminar</a></h1>
    <section class="header">
        June  1, 2021
    </section>
    <section>
        <p><strong>Friday, June 4th, 2021, 11:00, on Zoom.</strong></p>
<p><a href="https://robertabonacina.com/">Roberta Bonacina</a> (Tübingen)<br />
<em>Two-level type theory</em></p>
<p><em>Abstract:</em></p>
<p>Homotopy type theory (HoTT) extends Martin-Löf type theory with the univalence axiom, which establishes a tight connection between types and homotopy spaces and allows to identify isomorphic objects. Univalence has very useful applications, but it has also drawbacks: properties that are not invariant under homotopy cannot be expressed internally. An important case is the concept of semisimplicial types, whose definition is so far elusive in HoTT. Two-level type theory (2LTT) is a formal theory which allows constructions that require access to non-homotopy-invariant notions. It is composed of two separate levels of types related by a conversion function that preserves context extensions; the outer level is Martin-Löf type theory plus the uniqueness of identity proofs, and the inner level is HoTT. In this talk we will discuss the consequences of univalence, and introduce 2LTT as a way to overcome some difficulties. Then, we will introduce the notion of model for this system, and define the syntactical category as a first step to prove an initiality result for the syntax of 2LTT. The last part of the talk is based on a joint work-in-progress with Benedikt Ahrens and Nicolai Kraus.</p>
<p>The seminar will be held on Zoom. In order to get access to the Zoom meeting, please contact <a href="http://www.di.univr.it/?ent=persona&amp;id=21404&amp;lang=en">Peter Schuster</a> or <a href="https://www.di.univr.it/?ent=persona&amp;id=40478">Giulio Fellin</a>.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://www.logicverona.it//2021-06-04.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Dipartimento di Informatica</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Seminar</title>
    <link>https://www.logicverona.it//2021-04-14.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <h1><a href=/2021-04-14.html>Seminar</a></h1>
    <section class="header">
        April  7, 2021
    </section>
    <section>
        <p><strong>Wednesday, April 14th, 2021, 16:30, on Zoom.</strong></p>
<p><a href="https://www.unich.it/ugov/person/1731">Gianluca Amato</a> (Chieti-Pescara)<br />
<em>Universal Algebra in UniMath</em> (joint work with Marco Maggesi and Cosimo Perini Brogi)</p>
<p><em>Abstract:</em></p>
<p>In this talk we will report on recent experiments in implementing the basic notions of universal algebra in the Unimath library. Unimath is a replacement of the standard library of the Coq proof assistant based on the univalent foundations of mathematics. Since the use of general higher order inductive types is forbidden in Unimath, a relevant part of this work has been the implementation of terms as lists of function symbols in such a way that the operations on terms are computable by the standard Coq evaluation mechanism.</p>
<p>More information can be found in the <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2102.05952">preprint</a>.</p>
<p>The seminar will be held on Zoom. In order to get access to the Zoom meeting, please contact <a href="http://www.di.univr.it/?ent=persona&amp;id=21404&amp;lang=en">Peter Schuster</a> or <a href="https://www.di.univr.it/?ent=persona&amp;id=40478">Giulio Fellin</a>.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://www.logicverona.it//2021-04-14.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Dipartimento di Informatica</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Seminar</title>
    <link>https://www.logicverona.it//2021-04-12.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <h1><a href=/2021-04-12.html>Seminar</a></h1>
    <section class="header">
        April  7, 2021
    </section>
    <section>
        <p><strong>Monday, April 12th, 2021, 16:30, on Zoom.</strong></p>
<p><a href="https://www.gu.se/en/about/find-staff/thierrycoquand">Thierry Coquand</a> (Göteborg)<br />
<em>Sheaf models and constructive mathematics</em></p>
<p><em>Abstract:</em></p>
<p>Sheaf models over sites, introduced by Grothendieck in algebraic geometry, are also important in the meta-theory of intuitionistic mathematics for showing that some properties are not valid constructively or for providing models of the notion of choice sequences. In this talk, I would like to explain another use of sheaf models in constructive mathematics, suggested by Joyal in 1975, which is to provide a way to build an algebraic closure of an arbitrary field.</p>
<p>The seminar will be held on Zoom. In order to get access to the Zoom meeting, please contact <a href="http://www.di.univr.it/?ent=persona&amp;id=21404&amp;lang=en">Peter Schuster</a> or <a href="https://www.di.univr.it/?ent=persona&amp;id=40478">Giulio Fellin</a>.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://www.logicverona.it//2021-04-12.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Dipartimento di Informatica</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Seminar</title>
    <link>https://www.logicverona.it//2021-02-10.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <h1><a href=/2021-02-10.html>Seminar</a></h1>
    <section class="header">
        February  4, 2021
    </section>
    <section>
        <p><strong>Wednesday, February 10th, 2021, 16:30, on Zoom.</strong></p>
<p><a href="http://logica.uniroma3.it/pistone/">Paolo Pistone</a> (Bologna)<br />
<em>The Yoneda Reduction of Polymorphic Types (joint work with Luca Tranchini)</em></p>
<p><em>Abstract:</em></p>
<p>We explore a family of type isomorphisms in System F whose validity corresponds, semantically, to some form of the Yoneda isomorphism from category theory. These isomorphisms hold under theories of equivalence stronger than βη-equivalence, like those induced by parametricity and dinaturality. Based on such isomorphisms, we investigate a rewriting over types, that we call Yoneda reduction, which can be used to eliminate quantifiers from a polymorphic type, replacing them with a combination of monomorphic type constructors. We then demonstrate some applications of this rewriting to problems like counting the inhabitants of a type or characterizing program equivalence in some fragments of System F.</p>
<p>The seminar will be held on Zoom. In order to get access to the Zoom meeting, please contact <a href="http://www.di.univr.it/?ent=persona&amp;id=21404&amp;lang=en">Peter Schuster</a> or <a href="https://www.di.univr.it/?ent=persona&amp;id=40478">Giulio Fellin</a>.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2021 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://www.logicverona.it//2021-02-10.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Dipartimento di Informatica</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Seminar</title>
    <link>https://www.logicverona.it//2021-01-18.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <h1><a href=/2021-01-18.html>Seminar</a></h1>
    <section class="header">
        January 15, 2021
    </section>
    <section>
        <p><strong>Thursday, January 21st, 2021, 10:30, on Zoom.</strong> <strong>PLEASE NOTICE THAT THE TALK WAS POSTPONED</strong></p>
<p><a href="https://www.unibo.it/sitoweb/eugenio.orlandelli/en">Eugenio Orlandelli</a> (Bologna)<br />
<em>FULL CUT ELIMINATION AND INTERPOLATION FOR INTUITIONISTIC LOGIC WITH EXISTENCE PREDICATE</em></p>
<p><em>Abstract:</em></p>
<p>In previous work by Baaz and Iemhoff, a Gentzen calculus for intuitionistic logic with existence predicate is presented that satisfies partial cut elimination and Craig’s interpolation property; it is also conjectured that interpolation fails for the implication-free fragment. In this paper an equivalent calculus is introduced that satisfies full cut elimination and allows a direct proof of interpolation via Maehara’s lemma. In this way, it is possible to obtain much simpler interpolants and to better understand and (partly) overcome the failure of interpolation for the implication-free fragment.</p>
<p>The seminar will be held on Zoom. In order to get access to the Zoom meeting, please contact <a href="http://www.di.univr.it/?ent=persona&amp;id=21404&amp;lang=en">Peter Schuster</a> or <a href="https://www.di.univr.it/?ent=persona&amp;id=40478">Giulio Fellin</a>.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2021 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://www.logicverona.it//2021-01-18.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Dipartimento di Informatica</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Minicourse "Modal Logics and Intuitionistic Logic"</title>
    <link>https://www.logicverona.it//2020-08-short-course.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<article>
    <h1><a href=/2020-08-short-course.html>Minicourse "Modal Logics and Intuitionistic Logic"</a></h1>
    <section class="header">
        August  7, 2020
    </section>
    <section>
        <p><strong>Modal Logics and Intuitionistic Logic</strong><br />
<a href="https://www.philosophie.tu-berlin.de/menue/fachgebiete/theoretische_philosophie/priv_doz_dr_stefania_centrone/">Stefania Centrone</a> (TU Berlin)</p>
<p>The minicourse “Modal logics and intuitionistic logic” (12h) has been videoregistered in August 2020. Members of the University of Verona who wish to follow the course but are not authorised to access <a href="https://moodledidattica.univr.it/course/view.php?id=4217#section-4">this link</a> are kindly asked to contact <a href="https://www.di.univr.it/?ent=persona&amp;id=40478&amp;lang=it">Giulio Fellin</a>.</p>
<p><em>Abstract</em><br />
Modal logics capture concepts of necessity and possibility; intuitionistic logic models computation and construction. This minicourse is intended to introduce into both kinds of logic with particular attention on their interaction, from the angles of syntax and semantics but with a certain proof-theoretic flavour. One highlight will be Gödel’s embedding of intuitionistic propositional logic into the modal logic S4, which stood at the beginning of provability logic.</p>
    </section>
</article>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2020 15:30:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://www.logicverona.it//2020-08-short-course.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Dipartimento di Informatica</dc:creator>
</item>

    </channel>
</rss>
